This is ridiculous!
这也太夸张了吧
Einar! Wait, Einar.
埃纳尔 等等
Let's dig deeper and cut the roots.
我们再挖深一点 把根切断
It won't come out like this.
这样是不行的
Damn you...
该死的
It still won't budge.
它仍旧纹丝不动
Darn it!
去他的
A horse...
一匹马...
It's impossible without a horse, after all.
没有一匹马还是不行的
They let us borrow one to transport the timber,
他们借了一匹马给我们运送木材
so why don't we get a horse for grading the land?
我们何不去借一匹马来整地?
It makes no sense.
这样下去不是办法
That horse wasn't lent to us.
那匹马不是借给我们的
We were just forced to do the work meant for the farmhands.
我们还被迫去做了农场帮手的工作
What should we do, Einar?
我们该怎么办 埃纳尔?
Should we hold off on making a field and just cut the trees?
要不我们先不整地 专心砍树就好?
No, I'll ask them one more time.
不行 我再去求他们一次
Although it may be pointless.
虽然可能白跑一趟
You don't know when to give up, do you?
你就是不懂得何时该放手 对吧?
No means no!
不行就是不行
Yeah, but we got permission from Pater.
对了 但我们得到了帕特的许可
Pater?
帕特?
Darn that ex-slave...
那该死的前奴隶...
Anyway, it's a no.
总之...不行
We're using all the horses for other jobs.
这些马全都别有用途
We don't have enough to lend to you.
没有多余的马可以借给你们
It's no use, slaves.
没有用的 奴隶
Stop skipping work and go back to the forest.
别再偷懒了 快回森林里工作
Hello.
你好
Oh? I only heard one greeting.
我只听到一个人问好
The big one doesn't have any manners, as usual.
这个大块头一如往常地很没礼貌
Hey, I'm going to borrow a horse.
你好 我想借匹马
Okay.
好
First of all,
首先
you slaves are no different from cows and horses.
你们这群奴隶跟牛马没什么两样
The fact that a horse like you
像你这样做牛做马的人
is leasing land and managing a field is annoying in itself.
竟然能租地耕田 这件事本身就令人厌恶
Use your own bodies!
用你们自己的身体劳作吧
At this rate,
按照这种速度
we have to ask the master himself.
我们得去请求主人才行
We need a horse no matter what.
无论如何 我们都需要一匹马
Not just for the tree stumps, but to plow as well.
不只是为了拔树墩 犁田也需要
I'm not going to let their bullying stop me!
他们的恶行也阻止不了我!
But even if we're able to borrow a horse with the masters help,
就算我们得到主人的帮助 借到了马
it will upset the farmhands.
农场帮手们会很不爽
We'll be targeted even more.
他们会让我们的日子更不好过
Then what will we do? Do everything by manpower?
那我们该怎么办?一切靠人力?
Who knows how many years it will take to prepare the field.
谁知道光是整地 就要花上几年的时间?
The forest is still huge.
森林仍然很茂密
Maybe we can clear up more land before we start on the field?
或许我们先清出更多空地 再开始耕田?
Growing crops simultaneously would be impossible.
一边砍树一边种植农作是不可能的
Thorfinn!
托尔芬
Why are you so unmotivated?
你为什么总是这么打不起劲?
Don't you want freedom?
你难道不想要自由吗?
Even if it's impossible, we have to grow crops!
就算是不可能 我们仍然要这么做
Then we'll sell them to the master and buy our freedom.
然后我们才能把农作物 卖给主人 赎回自由
To do that we need a horse!
为了达成这个目标 我们就需要一匹马!
Einar, you are so energetic for someone
埃纳尔 作为一个 从没有好好吃过一顿饭的人来说
who doesn't get decent meals.
你的精力好充沛啊
Stupid!
笨蛋
Your lack of energy is more abnormal.
你意志消沉才是不正常
- I got the gist of it. - Huh?
-我大既知道是怎么一回事了 -嗯?
Up we go... Ouch...
准备起身啦...好痛啊
What are you doing? Come over here.
你们站在那里做什么?还不快过来
We can't talk if you're so far away.
你们离得这么远 我们无法交谈
Don't step on the ridges.
别踩在田垄上
Hello. Um, what can we do for you?
你好 我们能帮你什么忙呢?
- What's your name? - Oh yes...
-你们叫什么名字? -是...
- I'm Einar. - I'm Thorfinn.
-我叫埃纳尔 -我叫托尔芬
- Want to borrow one? - Huh?
-想要借一匹吗? -什么?
A horse. You need one, right?
你们需要一匹马 对吧?
Yes! We need one!
对 我们需要一匹马
No way! Are you serious?
不是吧 你是认真的吗?
That would be so helpful! Wow!
那真是帮了我们一个大忙 好耶!
More like...
就像是...
Sorry, um...
不好意思...
Who are you?
请问你是哪位?
This hurts your back.
这种工作很伤背
Um, grandpa?
这位老人家...
Call me Sverkel.
叫我斯威克
Don't forget to add a "Mr."
别忘了加上“先生”
Mr. Sverkel,
斯威克先生
for how long should we pick these rocks?
你要我们捡石头捡多久?
Until there are no rocks.
直到把石头捡光为止
Hey, your hands aren't moving.
喂 你的手都没在动
Oh, sorry.
噢 抱歉
Ouch...
好痛
Good.
很好
So, Mr. Sverkel,
那么 斯威克先生
about the horse you are going to lend us...
关于你要借给我们的那匹马...
Bring the basket.
把篮子带上
Once you're done chopping the firewood, go draw some water.
砍完木材之后再去挑一些水来
- Hurry now. - Yes!
-动作快 -好
He's totally taking advantage of us.
他根本是在占我们便宜
We don't have time for this.
我们可没有这种时间
More like, I wonder if that old man
我倒是忍不住怀疑 那位老人家
is living in this house alone?
是不是一个人住在这里?
I don't know. I've never met him before either.
我不知道 我之前也从没见过他
Will he really lend it to us?
他真的会借给我们一匹马吗?
What if he's just using us and making us work for free?
要是他只是趁机利用我们 帮他做白工呢?
Even if that's true, that's normal.
如果真是如此 也很正常
We're slaves, after all.
毕竟我们是奴隶
But we belong to the master.
但我们是主人的奴隶
I don't care about your status.
我才不在乎你们的阶级
This is a contract.
这是一份合约
I will lend you a horse and in exchange you will do my chores
我会借你们一匹马 作为交换
both when you borrow it and when you bring it back.
你们得在借马和还马的时候 帮我做家务
Got that?
懂了吗?
All right! Onto the next one!
好 下一个!
There we go!
来了!
This is so easy! Very nice!
太容易了 太好了!
I can't believe he actually lent us one.
我真不敢相信他真的把马借给我们了
That old man is such a nice person!
那个老人家人真好
There!
来了!
You can do it! That's it!
你可以的!很好!
You're so cute!
你好可爱喔!
All right!
好耶!
Next one!
下一个!
If we keep this up,
如果能保持这种进度
we may actually be able to sow in fall.
我们或许就能在秋天播种了
I wonder if that old man would lend us a plow too?
不知那个老人家 会不会也愿意借我们一把犁?
Preferably a heavy one with wheels.
最好是带轮子的重型耕犁
What seeds do you sow in fall?
秋天该播什么种?
Huh?
什么?
Wheat, of course.
当然是小麦咯
Interesting. Wheat is sown in fall, huh?
真有意思 小麦是在秋天播种喔?
What... Wait a second!
什么?等等
Have you worked in a field before?
你之前在田里工作过吗?
No.
没有
In my country, no one had fields.
在我的国家 没有人拥有农田
And I was working on the battlefield since I was a kid.
而且我从小就活在战场上
A country with no fields...
没有农田的国家...
Man, it's hard to believe.
天哪 真令人无法相信
My mom and little sister would be baffled if they heard that.
我妈和我妹妹听到这件事 一定会觉得很奇怪
Well, anyway!
也无所谓啦
When it comes to the fields, count on me!
关于种田的事 就交给我吧
- After all, I'm a professional! - Okay.
-毕竟我可是专业的 -好的
Hey, you slaves!
喂 奴隶
Who gave you permission to take that horse, huh?
谁允许你们用那匹马的?
- Here comes the jerk. - Hello.
-混球来了 -你好
We didn't take this without permission.
我们并非擅自取用
Mr. Sverkel lent it to us.
斯威克先生借给我们的
Huh? Who?
什么?谁?
I said Mr. Sverkel.
我说的是斯威克先生
His place is all the way down this path.
从这条路走下去就是他家
Stop lying!
别撒谎了
There's nobody named Sverkel here.
这里没有斯威克这个人
So you resorted to stealing, huh?
所以你们竟然用偷的?
Oh? Did we have a horse like this on our farm?
喔?我们的农场里有这种马吗?
Hey, who did you say you borrowed this horse from?
喂 你说马是向谁借来的?
Like I said...
我说过了
Mr. Sverkel! You don't know him?
是斯威克先生 你不认识他吗?
He's a bald, short old man.
他是个秃头矮小的老人家
Bald, short, old man?
秃头矮小的老人家?
Is it the old master?
是老主人吗?
Oh, now that you mention it, his name was something like that.
对哦 你这么一说 那好像就是他的名字
The old master?
老主人?
You must be lying after all.
你们果然在说谎
He's such a grumpy man.
他是个脾气暴躁的人
He would never lend you a horse.
绝对不可能把马借给你们
He's Master Ketil's father.
他是凯特尔主人的父亲
He's the most important person on this farm.
他是这座农场里地位最高的人
Looks like it's going to rain.
看起来要下雨了
Thorfinn, after we're done with this row, let's call it a day.
托尔芬 这一排做完之后就收工吧
Okay.
好
It's a root again.
又是根
We removed the stumps,
我们移走了树墩
but there are still roots deep underground.
但地底下仍然盘根错节
Oh well...
那么...
This year we'll only plow a thin layer.
今年我们只能浅耕
I don't want to take a chance and break the plow we're borrowing.
我可不想冒险 弄坏我们借来的犁
Wow...
真厉害...
That wilderness turned into this in just one day.
这片荒野在一天之内 就变成了这个样子
Look, over there,
你看那里
over there,
那里
and there. They're using two.
还有那里 他们用了两把
They bought four more this year,
他们今年又买了四把
so there are a total of ten heavy plows.
所以总共有十把重型耕犁
The master must be extremely wealthy.
主人一定很有钱
Are these that expensive?
这些工具很贵吗?
They sure are!
那还用说?
In my village, one was shared by eight families.
在我的村子里 八个家庭共用一把
I'm so glad the old master had one at his house.
我真高兴老主人家里有一把
There is no way the farmhands would let us borrow one.
农场帮手绝对不可能借给我们
I imagine it's difficult to cultivate the land by hand
用锄头徒手耕田
using a hoe.
是件很困难的事吗?
Of course it is.
当然咯
Having this and a horse makes a world of difference.
有了犁和马 可是天壤之别
What an amazing invention.
真是个了不起的发明
This must have been invented by a farmer.
一定是农夫发明的
You must know the hardships of farming in order to make
得很懂耕田之苦 才能想到这样的办法
something like this.
发明出这样的工具
You really are a newbie at farming, aren't you?
你真的是个新手农夫 对吧?
Everything is a new discovery for you.
每件事都是一个新发现
You're like a big baby.
你真像个大孩子
It's starting to rain!
开始下雨了
Let's hurry, Thorfinn!
动作快 托尔芬
Are you prepared for the rain?
你做好下雨的准备了吗?
Don't change the subject.
别转移话题
I'm worried about your health, Dad.
爸 我很担心你的健康
You're too old to be overworking yourself.
你年纪太大了 不适合过度操劳
When you collapsed on the field last time,
你上次在田里倒下的时候
you were lucky that Snake happened to be there.
是运气好 蛇刚好经过那里
If I can die on the field, I will have no complaints.
如果能死在田里 我不会有一句怨言
First of all, it's reckless for you to live on your own at that age.
再说了 你这把年纪了 还一个人住 实在太不像话了
You can't do physical labor.
你也做不了体力活
You don't need to worry about that. I am managing.
这个不用你担心 我自己会看着办
Dad, don't be difficult.
爸 别为难我了
Ketil,
凯特尔
you and I don't think the same way.
我们对事情有不同的看法
If we are together, we'll start fighting again.
如果住在一起的话 我们又会再起争执
You're just stubborn!
你就是太固执了
This is kind of awkward.
有点尴尬
About what we talked about... Give it some thought.
关于我们谈过的事 你好好考虑一下
Hm? What are you two doing here?
咦?你们两个在这里做什么?
Hello.
您好
Dad, don't just use them as you please.
爸 请不要任意使唤他们
They're my slaves.
他们是我的奴隶
You're wet.
你们全身都湿了
Might as well wash your clothes while you're here.
不如刚好在这里把衣服洗了吧
I guess those two don't get along.
我猜那两位处得不太好
All right, where's the washpot...
好的 洗盆在哪里呢?
- Whoa! - What's wrong?
-天啊 -怎么了?
- Snake! It's Snake! - A snake?
-蛇 是蛇! -有蛇?
- Why is he here? - Uh...
-他怎么会在这里? -不是...
More like, he was dead asleep through that fight?
我说...外面吵成那样 他还能睡成这样?
He must have thick skin.
他的脸皮一定很厚
What a messy sleeper.
睡相真差
Gramps, you're making food, aren't you!
老头子 你在煮饭 对吧?
- Don't think you can eat without me! - Darn. You woke up.
-别以为你能独自享用 -可恶 你醒了
Why are you two here? Were you trying to sneak into bed with me?
你们两个怎么会在这里? 想偷偷溜上我的床?
Good morning.
早安
You are hopeless...
你真是没救了
You only wake up when it's mealtime.
总是在吃饭时间才会醒来
Aren't you ashamed of yourself?
你不觉得这样很可耻吗?
How could a grown man like you
你都是个成熟的大人了
shamelessly eat a meal without doing any work.
怎么还能够厚颜无耻地在这 白吃白喝?
That's nonsense, Gramps.
胡说八道 老头子
Thieves come at night.
小偷晚上才会出现
Peace is maintained on the farm
农场能平安无事
because we patrol every night.
是因为我们在晚上巡逻
And so I will eat.
所以我吃得心安理得
You just hang out with girls in their houses. How is that "guard duty"?
你只是跑去女孩家里鬼混 这样也叫巡逻?
I'm on guard to make sure the girls aren't taken by thieves.
我是去女孩家里巡逻 确保她们不会被盗贼抓走
You always have a cheeky comeback.
你总是很会回嘴
You always have something to nag about.
你总是唠叨个不停
What are you guys doing? Come over here and eat.
你们两个站在那里做什么? 过来吃饭吧
Aren't you hungry?
你们不饿吗?
Is it okay?
可以吗?
Eat up! You don't have to feel bad, it's nothing special.
快吃吧 不用不好意思 只是粗茶淡饭
It's not for you to say!
这话轮不到你说
Sit down. People who work deserve to eat.
坐下吧 付出劳动的人就有资格吃饭
Um, is it true that thieves come here?
这里真的会出现盗贼吗?
Yes, they come all the time.
对 一直都有
They target the wheat that's ready for harvesting and pigs.
他们的目标是 已经可以收割的小麦和猪
I see...
原来如此
Some of them are armed.
有些身上还带着兵器
Beating them up and detaining them
把他们揍一顿之后关起来
is part of our job.
也是我们的工作之一
We are actually working, you see.
我们的确在好好工作 你懂吗?
The amount we would potentially lose to thieves is basically the same amount
我们会被盗贼偷走的粮食数量 基本上跟喂食
it costs to feed you guys.
你们这群人的成本差不多
Old man...
臭老头
Must you be so annoying?
你一定要这么讨人厌吗?
We can chase away thieves without your help.
不用你们帮忙 我们也能赶走盗贼
We are Nordic men.
我们可是北方人
We know how to use a sword and spear.
我们知道如何用剑用矛
Really? You can have a swordfight at your age?
真的吗?你都这把老骨头了 还能动刀动剑?
Don't flatter yourself, Snake.
别自以为是了 蛇
There are countless people who are more skilled than you.
比你厉害的人多的是
I'm just worried about you because you're old.
我只是在担心你 毕竟你老了
I'm not frail enough to need you to worry about me.
我还没虚弱到需要你担心的程度
Don't get so worked up. You'll collapse again, Grandpa.
别那么激动 你会再度倒下的 老爷爷
Say what you will, but the truth is
不管你说什么 事实就是
that the force on this farm doesn't match up to its size.
以这座农场的大小来说 现有的武力是不够的
I have 13 subordinates
我有13名部下
and our hands are full with thieves.
得应付为数众多的盗贼
Let's say, 50 to 60 soldiers attack us,
要是有50或60名的士兵 前来攻击我们
this farm won't stand a chance.
这座农场根本无法抵抗
- Right, Thorfinn? - Huh?
-对吧 托尔芬? -什么?
Right... Well, I wouldn't know.
这个嘛...我怎么会知道?
We won't have to face anything worse
这座农场也不会出现比盗贼
than thieves here.
更难缠的对象
You never know!
那可很难说
When that happens, it'll be too late to panic.
一旦遇上的话 连恐慌的时间都没有
Don't worry.
别担心
Whatever happens, I will not beg for your help.
不管发生什么事 我都不会求你帮忙
Why won't anything worse than thieves come here?
为什么不会出现比盗贼难缠的对手?
S... Sorry...
对不起...
Because of King Harald's authority.
因为哈罗德国王的关系
Ketil sends an exorbitant amount
凯特尔家族一年会向国王
of tribute to the king twice a year.
上缴两次价值惊人的贡品
As long as the king accepts it,
只要国王收下
he has an obligation to protect Ketil.
他就有义务保护凯特尔家族
It is foolish...
用钱买和平...
to buy peace with money.
太愚蠢了
What is the point of owning a farm that is too big for a farmer
农夫拥有一座大到 自己保护不了的农场
to protect?
有什么意义呢?
Do you know how many days
你们知道从耶林
it takes to get here from Jelling?
过来这里要几天吗?
We are the ones who are actually protecting the farm.
保护这座农场的人是我们才对
Too much wealth brings forth disaster.
太多的财富会带来灾祸
Did you just ignore me?
你把我当空气吗?
When you increase your wealth you fear losing it.
你的财富不断增加 你就会越来越害怕失去它
To deal with that fear you use money. Then you try to earn more.
只好用钱来消除恐惧 然后再想办法赚更多钱
My stupid son doesn't realize how futile that is.
我那傻儿子还没认清这只是白忙一场
My goodness,
绕了我吧
old men love to lecture people.
老头子就是爱教训别人
Oh! It stopped raining!
雨停了
All right! I guess I'll go do some guard duty.
好的 我该出门巡逻了
Don't come back!
不用回来了
I know you get lonely when I don't visit.
我知道我没来看你的时候 你会很寂寞
Get out already!
快给我滚
What a strange duo.
这一对还真妙
They seem to get along better than the real father and son.
他们的感情似乎比亲父子更好
Yeah.
对呀
I feel like
我感觉...
I learned a lot of things today.
我今天学到了很多
Good for you, big baby.
那就好 大孩子
Don't call me that.
不要那样叫我
Too much wealth, huh?
太多的财富?
You can sow them more thoroughly.
你可以再多播一些种子
But this is all we have, right?
但我们就只有这些种子 对吧?
It's fine!
没关系
Don't hold back.
不用克制
Trust what your friend tells you.
相信朋友说的话就对了
- Friend? - What?
-朋友? -什么?
No way.
不是吧
What's with that reaction? We're friends, right?
干嘛出现这种反应? 我们是朋友 对吧?
Am I wrong?
我错了吗?
No, you're right...
你说得对
we're friends.
我们是朋友
"Iron Fist Ketil."
铁拳凯特尔
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译:朱未耒